<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DevOps on tomis9&#39;s cookbook</title>
    <link>https://tomis9.github.io/tags/devops/</link>
    <description>Recent content in DevOps on tomis9&#39;s cookbook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2018 15:01:35 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tomis9.github.io/tags/devops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>git</title>
      <link>https://tomis9.github.io/git/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2018 15:01:35 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomis9.github.io/git/</guid>
      <description>1. What is git and why would you use it?  Git is a totally basic program if you think seriously about programming. Seriously.
 It&amp;rsquo;s a version control system, which makes:
 working on the same project with many people simple;
 remembers the whole history of the projects, i.e. all it&amp;rsquo;s chages as long as you follow git&amp;rsquo;s discipline
   2. A &amp;ldquo;Hello world&amp;rdquo; example As you may have noticed, my posts usually contain a section called &amp;lsquo;A &amp;ldquo;Hello World&amp;rdquo; example&amp;rsquo;, but not this time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pyenv, virtualenv, freeze</title>
      <link>https://tomis9.github.io/pyenv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 15:32:40 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomis9.github.io/pyenv/</guid>
      <description>1. What are pyenv, virtualenv and freeze and why would you use them?  these three Python packages let you install your favourite Python version with your favourite Python packages&amp;rsquo; versions on any machine independently to those already installed on the system; you can even store many Python versions and Python packages&amp;rsquo; versions;
 pyenv let&amp;rsquo;s you install any Python version you like;
 virtualenv let&amp;rsquo;s you install any Python&amp;rsquo;s package version you like;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>packages</title>
      <link>https://tomis9.github.io/packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2018 12:06:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomis9.github.io/packages/</guid>
      <description>1. What are R packages and why would you use them?  R packaging is a convenient way to store and share your R code.
 It lets you incorporate testing with testthat specially prepared tools (you can use testthat without creating a package, but it&amp;rsquo;s slightly more complicated).
 It lets you easily list dependencies with packrat. You can also achieve this without using a package.
 You can easily version your code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>testing</title>
      <link>https://tomis9.github.io/testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2018 12:02:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomis9.github.io/testing/</guid>
      <description>1. What is testing and why would you use it?  testing or test-driven development (TDD) is a discipline, which relies on writing a test for every functionality before creating it;
 at first the test will fail, as we have not provided the proper functionality yet. Our goal is to fulfill this functionality, so the test will pass.
  In reality you modify your tests as you create the functionality or even write the tests after you are finished writing it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>